嘿，你们好，我是TheCherno，欢迎回到我的OpenGL系列教程
hey, what's up guys, my name is TheCherno and welcome back to my OpenGL series
那么我们已经完成了混合和纹理
so we've done blending, we've done textures
以及顶点数组，索引缓冲区和顶点缓冲区
we've done vertex arrays, index buffers, vertex buffers
这些我们都做过了
we've done all of this stuff
我们得到了在屏幕上渲染的东西了
we've got stuff rendering on our screen
但我们实际上还没有触及图形编程中最重要的一个部分
but we haven't actually even touched on one of the biggest parts of graphics programming
就是数学，如果你们一直跟着我们学习的话
maths or math, if you're from the us
那么数学是什么，我们为什么要用它
so what is maths, why do we use it
比如我们如何使用它，为什么需要它
like how can we use it, and why do we even need it
那么数学通常被用在图形编程的个个领域
so maths in general is used in pretty much every area of graphics programming
随着这个系列的继续，我们开始处理一些东西
and as this series continues, and we start dealing with things
我们实际上需要开始实现我们自己的算法
we'll actually have to start implementing our own kind of algorithms
包括数学和计算，所有这些
that involve maths and doing calculations, and all of that
我敢肯定，任何刚刚接触OpenGL的人
I'm fairly sure that anyone who is new to OpenGL
或你们在做图形编程
or you do graphics programming
也许他们的脑子里有个想法，认为数学是必须的
probably has an idea in their head, that maths is going to be required
我们将开始深入这些话题
and we are going to start diving into those topics
但是今天我们要讲的是数学在一般情况下是如何应用的
but today we're just going to kind of talk about how maths use in general
从数学库开始，写一些真正有用的代码
and get started with a math library, and actually write some code that does something
那么数学，当我谈到图形编程中的数学时
so math, when I talk about math in graphics programming
我确实要说一说数学的两个不同领域
I'm really talking about two different kind of areas of maths
或者是矩阵和向量这两个不同的概念
or two different concepts that we have matrixes and vectors
矩阵，矩阵本质上是一个数字数组
now matrixes, a matrix is essentially an array of numbers
我们可以通过乘法来处理，或者我们可以用不同的方法来设置，对吧
that we can kind of manipulate by multiplying, or we can set up in various ways, right
它实际上就是一个数字数组
it is literally an array of numbers
当我们用这些数乘以其他数，我们得到一组新的数
and when we multiply those numbers by something else, we get a new set of numbers
这些计算可以用于一些事情，比如在一个3D世界中定位物体
and those calculations can be useful for things, like positioning objects in a 3D world
在另一边的向量
on the flip side vectors
在图形编程中，我们要处理两种类型的向量，并且我知道
there are two types of vectors that we deal with in graphics programming, and I know
因为我一直收到很多关于这方面的评论
because I get a lot of comments about this all the time
所以我们要花点时间快速地讲一下它们
so we are going to take the time to quickly talk about them
这是方向向量，这是位置向量，对吧
there's directional vectors, and there's positional vectors, right
所以向量可以指代一些你们可能已经习惯了的东西
so a vector can refer to something that you're probably used to
如果你们完成了一些学习
if you've done something
比如工程数学，或者高中数学，或者取决于不同的国家
like engineering maths, or high school maths, or depending on different countries
他们是怎么教的，你知道的所有这些
how they teach, you know that and all of that
但本质上，一个向量
but essentially, a vector
它在区域上被看作是一个方向，一个大小或长度，对吧
it's regionally seen as like a direction and a magnitude or a length, right
所以你们可能会
so you're probably
如果你们是学了数学过来的，可能已经习惯了听到向量之类的东西
if you if you're coming from actual maths, you're probably used to hearing about a vector as like
你们知道，指向某个地方，像字面方向向量，图形编程可以是那样的
you know, pointing somewhere, like a literal direction vectors, and graphics programming can be that
但它们也可以是2D，3D或4D空间中的位置，对吧
but they can also be just positions in either a 2D, 3D or 4D space, right
那么举个例子，我有这么一个向量，大概是(200, 100)
so for example, I could have a vector, that's like 200, 100
那意味着它是屏幕上的一个点
and what that means is that it's a point on my screen
大概是从左边往里200像素，从下面往上100像素
that's like 200 pixels in from the left, and 100 pixels up from the bottom
那也是一个向量
that is also a vector
所以你们一定要习惯那些术语
so you should definitely get used to that terminology
至于向量和矩阵
vectors and matrixes
我用了很多，但我想说的可能是最常见和最重要的用法
I used a lot, but I would say probably the most common usage and the most important usage
尤其是当你们刚刚开始接触变换的时候
especially when you're just beginning is for transformation
所以我们以后会用图表更详细地讨论这个
so we are definitely going to talk about this in much more detail with like diagrams
以及我们所有的东西
and all of our stuff in the future
但是这个变换本质上是我们得到顶点缓冲的一种方法
but the transformation is essentially a way that we can get our vertex buffer
以及所有的点，所有的顶点都变成了我们在屏幕上看到的某种形式
with all of its points, and all of the vertices into some kind of form that we see on our screen
我们需要变换的原因有很多
the reason that we need transformation is for a number of reasons
首先，让我们看看，我们有一个巨大的3D世界，有一个球，对吧
first of all, let's just see, we have a massive 3D world, and we have a ball, right
我们需要在3D世界中定位这个球
we need to position that ball somewhere in the 3D world
如果我们有一个移动的相机呢
what if we have a camera moving around
也许它是绕着球转的，对吧，它的工作方式就是那样的
maybe it's orbiting around the ball, right, the way that that works is that well
其实这儿根本就没有相机这回事
there's no such thing as a camera really
我们真正需要做的是移动世界和球
what we need to do really is just move the world and the ball around
所以我们改变了世界和球的位置
so we change the position of the world and the ball
这是一种疯狂的幻觉，相机旋转或围绕着我们的目标
and that kind of crazy illusion of a camera circling, or orbiting our our subject
我们可能还想以某种方式定位顶点，那不仅仅是变换
we might want to also position vertices in a way, that isn't just a translation
可能是缩放，或者我们想要旋转
it might be something like scale, or we want to rotate things
所有这些都需要数学来完成，而我们如果
all of that stuff requires maths to actually accomplish, and the reason that we if
我的意思是，如果我们运行我们现在拥有的东西
I mean if we launched the thing that we have right now
你们可以看到没有3D世界或其他东西，我们只有这个ChernoLogo
you can see that we don't really have like a 3D world or anything, we have this ChernoLogo
然而，纵横比是完全错误的，因为默认情况下
however the aspect ratio is completely wrong, because by default
OpenGL给了我们一个-1到1的投影矩阵
OpenGL gives us a projection matrix of -1 to 1
这种假设窗口实际上是方形的
which kind of assumes that the window is actually square
我们的窗口不是正方形的，是640x480像素，意味着它的纵横比是4:3
our window is not square, is 640 by 480 pixels, which means it has a 4 3 aspect ratio
4:3，对吧，不是1:1
4:3, right, not 1 to 1
所以即使是像这样的小事，我们也需要变换
so even for something as trivial as this, we also need a transformation
我们需要让我们的几何图形不像我们的窗口是正方形的
we need to actually make our geometry not be as if our window was square
我们需要改变我们绘制的这个四边形
we need to actually kind of change this quad that we're drawing here
然后应用纹理
and applying the texture to it
这样它的纵横比才适合我们的显示器
so that it's the right aspect ratio to fit our monitor
即使是我们的窗口，即使那需要变换，所以很多的变换正在发生
even though our window, even that requires a transformation, so a lot of transformation is happening
不管怎么说，我整天都在谈论数学，以及它是如何使用的
anyway, I consider talking all day about maths, and how it's used
随着本系列的继续，你们将会看到
you will see as this series continues
我们直接开始吧，用一个数学库
let's just jump into it, and let's use a maths library
让我们现在就来解决我们在ChernoLogo上遇到的这种变换问题
and let's just fix for now this kind of transformation issue we have with the ChernoLogo
那么我要用一个数学库，它是免费的，叫做glm
so I'm going to be using a maths library, that's free, it's called glm
你们可以找到这个，我会把链接留在下面的描述中
you can find this, I'll leave the link in the description below
这是一个OpenGL数学库，其实你们用什么数学库并不重要
this is specifically an OpenGL mathematics library, doesn't really matter what maths library you use
只要它可以运行，并且包含我们需要的所有功能
as long as it's something that works, and contains all the features we need
通常，如果我在编写自己的引擎，我可能会编写自己的数学库
typically if I was writing my own engine, I probably write my own math library
那会更有意义
that makes a lot of sense
至于OpenGL，为什么要用那个库
OpenGL, the reason
这是因为这个很好，因为它是OpenGL特定的
this one's good is because it's OpenGL specific
这意味着，例如，矩阵是列主排序的
which means that, for example, the matrixes are column-major ordering
所以实际矩阵在内存中布局的方式是OpenGL期望的
so the way that the actual matrix is laid out in memory is in a way that OpenGL kind of expects it to be
不需要做任何形式的变换或者叫做转置
and doesn't need to do any kind of transformation or as it's called transposition transposing
把它转换成正确的格式
to actually convert it into the right format
如果我使用一个数学库，如果我有一个带有许多不同显卡接口的引擎
if I was using a math, if I had an engine with a lot of different graphics apis
我可能会选择行主排序
I'd probably opt for a row major ordering
因为这对于CPU端乘法之类的来说更友好一些
because that can be a little bit more friendly for CPU side multiplication and all that
我们就不多讲了，我想说的是，如果你们不喜欢glm
we're not going to talk too much about this, what I'm saying is if you don't like glm
或者如果你们想使用其他库，请随意，我只是在使用glm
or if you want to use a different library, feel free to, I'm just using glm
因为它似乎是标准的OpenGL数学库
because it seems to be the standard kind of OpenGL maths library
并且在这一点上，我倒是不怎么在乎，因为这对我来说够用就行
and at this point, I don't care, because it works for what I need
所以在这里，我要去releases，在这里
so over here, I'm going to go to releases, which is over here
然后点击这里的zip文件下载最新版本
and then download this latest release by just clicking on the zip file over here
一旦我下载完成后，在zip文件中
and once I've got it downloaded, inside the zip file
我们有一个glm文件夹，里面有很多不同的东西
we have a glm folder inside there, we have a bunch of different things
我只关心glm文件夹中的实际代码
I really only care about the actual code which is in the glm folder
那么复制glm文件夹，然后到OpenGL项目的位置
so I'm going to copy that glm folder, I'm going to then go to the location of my OpenGL project
然后在src/vendor，我将粘贴glm源代码
and then on the src/vendor, I'm going to paste in that glm source code
因此，glm是一个只包含头文件的库，这意味着没有cpp文件
so glm is a header only library, which means there are no cpp files
我们根本不需要编译它
we don't need to compile it at all
它会被包含或像那样被编译
it's going to be included or kind of get compiled like that
所以我们不需要链接到库，或创建cpp文件，就像用stb_image那样
so we don't have to link against a library, or kind of create a cpp file, like we did with stb_image
这个东西真的很容易使用，让我们直接进入它
this stuff is really easy to use, and let's just get right into it
那么一旦我把它粘贴在这里
so once I've got this pasted over here
我要做的是右键点击OpenGL，到属性
one thing I will do is I'll right click on OpenGL, go to properties
在C/C++通用的所有配置下
and under all configurations here in C/C++ general
我将把src\vendor添加到实际的附加包含目录中
I'm just going to add src\vendor to my actual additional include directory
这样我就不需要每次我想要包含一个文件时都输入vendor
so that I don't have to type vendor every time I want to include a file
那么我们看到了这个，在Texture.cpp中，包含了vendor/stb_image
so we kind of saw this, I guess in the Texture.cpp file, we included vendor/stb_image
我们不再需要那样做了，我们可以那样做，那样应该没问题
we don't need to do that, anymore, we can just do stb_image like that, and that should work fine
因为我们已经添加了编译器的包含目录
because we've added that compiler include directory
我在这里刷新一下我的项目
I'm just gonna refresh my project over here
现在我想在我的项目的实际解决方案中包含这些文件
now I do want to include this like all of these files in my actual solution in my project
我的意思是，反正它们也不会被编译
I mean they're not gonna get compiled anyway
但我还是希望它们能给出搜索结果之类的
but I still want them to come up with searches and all of that
否则，如果我，你们知道的，按ctrl shift f，我想搜索glm之类的
so otherwise if I, you know, press like control shift f, and I want to search for like glm or something
我想搜索我所有的文件
I wanted to actually search all of my files
但是在gtc里面有一个文件，我认为它是或者可能在gtx里
however there is a file inside gtc, I think it is or maybe it's in gtx、
有个dummy.cpp文件，上面说它是一个只包含头文件的库
yeah, there's this dummy.cpp file, which just says that it's a header only library
这只是一种暗示，如果你们往下滚动
and this is just for kind of semic, if you scroll down
你们会看到它确实有一个主函数，它会影响我们的主函数
you'll see it actually does have a main function, that will interfere with our main function
所以我们右键点击这个文件，然后点击从项目中移除
so let's just right-click with that file and hit exclude from project
因为我们显然不想编译它，好了，酷
because we obviously don't want to compile that, okay, cool
总之，我们有了glm，运行的是非常简单的东西
so anyway, we've got glm and running really easy stuff
我现在要做的是在我的Application.cpp文件中使用它
what I'm going to do now is actually use it inside my Application.cpp file
我们解决ChernoLogo问题的方法是
the way that we're going to fix our issue with the ChernoLogo is
通过一个叫做投影矩阵的东西
by using something called a projection matrix
投影矩阵是我们告诉窗口的一种方式
now a projection matrix is a way for us to actually tell our window
我们想要如何将所有不同的顶点映射到它
how we want to map all of our different vertices to it
所以我们有一个填充了顶点位置顶点缓冲区这样的概念
so we have this concept of having a vertex buffer filled with vertex positions
但是我们需要把它转换到2D平面
however we need to obviously transform that into some kind of 2D plane
因为当我们把它绘制在笔记本电脑屏幕或电脑显示器上时
because when we draw it on our laptop screen or on our computer monitor
我们需要它以2D的方式绘制出来
we need it to actually be drawn in a 2D way
那么想象一个3D世界，我们有一个3D世界的数学表示
so picture a 3D world, right, we have this mathematical representation of a 3D world
但我们需要把它绘制在2D表面上
but we need to draw it on a 2D surface
那么数学是如何计算的，对吧
so how does the maths work for that, right
我们如何从3D几何图形到2D平面图形
how do we go from having this 3D geometry to having a flat kind of 2D drawing
那就是投影矩阵的用处
that is what a projection matrix is useful
以后的视频中，我们会详细图解这些东西
and we'll definitely dive into the details and diagrams and all that stuff in a future video
但我们需要解决这个问题的方法基本上是告诉
but the way that we need to fix this problem is by basically telling
所有构成ChernoLogo的顶点位置
all of our kind of vertex positions that make up their ChernoLogo
嘿，我们绘制所在这个窗口实际上不是一个正方形，它是4 × 3的
that hey, the window that we're drawing on to isn't actually a square, it's 4 by 3
那么我们可能做一些计算让那个运行，所以如果我们往下看
so maybe do some maths to make that work, so if we go down here
我们要实现那个的方法很简单
the way that we're really going to do that is pretty simple
首先，我要在这里输入glm/glm.hpp包含glm
first of all, I'm going to include the glm over here by typing in glm/glm.hpp
我们还需要包含一个，我想是glm/gtc/matrix_transform.hpp
and we actually need one more include, which I think is gtc/matrix_transform
好了，酷，我们在这里包含了两个头文件，现在向下滚动
okay, cool, so we've included two header files here, now if we scroll down
我现在要做的就是开始创建我们所有的统一变量
what I'm going to do here is where we actually start to create all of our uniforms
我要创建一个，我要创建我的投影矩阵
I'm going to create a, want to create my projection matrix
我把这个叫做glm::mat4，那是它的类型，这是一个4×4矩阵
I'm going to call this glm::mat4, that's the type, it's a 4 by 4 matrix
我们将它命名为proj，我想把它设为glm::ortho()
we're going to call it proj, and I want to set it equal to glm::ortho()
这将会产生一个叫做正交矩阵的东西
this is going to create something called an orthographic matrix
现在对于左边和右边，我的意思是，首先是左边，右边，底部，顶部
now for the left and right, we just I mean first left right bottom top
我们真的只需要指定一些东西，但遵循4x3的纵横比
we really just need to specify something, but adheres to that 4 by 3 aspect ratio
那么，左边是-2，右边是2
so I'm going to use something like -2 for the left, 2 for the right
底部是-1.5，顶部是1.5，至于远近
-1.5 for the bottom, and then 1.5 for the top, and we, for near and far
我们可以指定-1和1
we can just specify something like -1 and 1
我们不需要指定那个，但是我们可以，好了
we don't need to specify that, but we can, okay
所以如果把这两个数都乘以2，就得到4 × 3
so if you multiply both of these numbers by 2, you'll get four by three
那基本上就是我的理解
that's essentially my reasoning here
我刚创建了一个从窗口顶部到底部有3个单位距离的东西
I've just created something that has a distance of 3 units from the top to bottom of the window
从左到右有4个单元距离
and 4 units from the left and right
这是一个4x3的纵横比，应该能固定所有的顶点位置
so it's a four by three aspect ratio, which should fix all of our vertex positioning
一个正交矩阵本质上就是把所有的坐标映射到2D平面上的一种方法
now an orthographic matrix is just essentially a way to map all of our coordinates onto a 2D plane
离得更远的物体并不会变小
where objects that are further away do not actually get smaller
这和我们习惯的透视投影是相反的
this is opposed to like a perspective projection which is what we're kind of used to
看看如果我们在现实生活中拍一张照片，远处的物体实际上很小，比如
seeing if we take a photograph in real life, where objects that are further away are actually small, like
这是我们用于3D渲染的东西，他对2D渲染很感兴趣
that's something that we use for 3D rendering, which is interested in kind of 2D rendering he has
所以我们不需要这个功能
so we don't need that functionality
正交矩阵和透视投影本身就是一个话题
orthographic and perspective projection is a bit of a topic in itself
我们肯定会讲那个并比较它们的不同之处
we'll definitely cover that and compare the differences
那么另一个提醒就是，这个视频只是对这些的介绍
so another reminder that, this video is just an introduction to all of this
我只是想做一个实用的介绍
I just like to give a practical introduction
这样我们就能在屏幕上看到一些东西
so that we can actually get something on the screen
你们可以修改这些数字，自己来玩吧
you can tinker with the numbers and play around with it yourself
我们一定会深入研究这个东西的
we will definitely dive into this stuff
可能会从下一期开始，还有所有这些东西，好了
probably beginning with like the next episodes and all that stuff, okay
那么一旦我得到了这个proj，我需要在我的着色器中使用它
so once I've got this proj, I need to use it in my shader
因为这是我真正想尝试做的
because what I'm really trying to do
我当然可以在CPU端做乘法
I could of course do the multiplication on the CPU side
实际上就是把所有这些顶点位置乘以这个矩阵
and actually just multiply all of these vertex positions by this matrix
或者说把它们转化成vec2或者vec4
or specifically convert these into basically vec2 or vec4
然后用这个矩阵做乘法
and then do the multiplication with this matrix
不过我要在着色器中做这个，如果我去Basic.shader这儿
however I'm actually going to do that in the shader, so if I go to my Basic.shader here
我要添加一个统一变量，这样我就可以把CPU的矩阵放到着色器里
I'm going to add a uniform, so that I can take in that matrix from the cpu into our shader
我将它命名为，uniform mat4，那是类型，就是u_MVP
I'm going to call it, uniform mat4, that's the type, u_MVP
这是我们的模型视图投影矩阵
which is going to be our model view projection matrix
模型视图投影矩阵现在这个特定的部分只是包含一个投影矩阵
model view projection matrix now this specific part of it were just including a projection matrix
不是视图矩阵或模型矩阵
not a view matrix or a model matrix
我以后会讲到这些可爱的东西
I'm gonna talk all about that lovely stuff in the future
我要做的就是用这个矩阵乘以我的顶点位置
and what I'm going to do with this matrix is just multiply my vertex positions with it
我们在顶点着色器中，每个顶点运行一次
we're in the vertex shader, this runs once per vertexed
我们要做的是我们要取这个顶点位置，它来自于顶点缓冲区
and what we're going to do is we're going to take this vertex position, that comes in from our vertex buffer
然后把它和投影矩阵相乘
and just multiply it with our projection matrix
将把它移到合适的空间
that's going to move it into the appropriate space
基于我们提供的正交矩阵
based on that orthographic matrix that we've actually provided
那么回到我们的源代码
so back in our source code over here
我们需要一种方法来设置统一变量，所以我们有一个SetUniform4f
we now need a way to actually set that uniform, so we have a SetUniform4f
这个对于vec4是合适的
which is fine for a vec4
但我们真正需要的是，一个SetUniformMatrix4f或者叫Mat4f
but what we really need is something, that is a SetUniformMatrix4f or just Mat4f I'll call it
我们要设置的统一变量的名称是u_MVP
and this is going to be called, what the uniform is called you want to set is u_MVP
然后我想说的值就是这个glm矩阵
and then the value that I want to say is just this glm matrix
那么我将传入proj，这是我们现在需要创建的函数
so I'll just pass in proj, that's the function that we now need to create
所以当我们来到这里的着色器类
so if we're going to our Shader class over here
我将添加函数SetUniformMat4f，我将保留这个const string& name
I'm going to add that function SetUniformMat4f, I'll leave this const string name
然后我添加一个就像那样的const glm::mat4& matrix
and then I'll just add a const glm::mat4 matrix just like that
我们向上滚动到顶部，像那样包含glm/glm.hpp
and we'll scroll up to the top, and include glm/glm.hpp like that
好了，很酷，那么回到Shader的cpp文件
okay, pretty cool, so back in our cpp file for our Shader
我们将把函数定义加到这里
we're going to just add that function definition here
我只是在用VA获取签名
I'm just using the visual assistant to get the signature
现在这个是glUniformMat4fv，这个v是，哦，实际上是Matrix4fv
and now this is going to be glUniformMat4fv, the v kind of, oh, that's actually Matrix4fv
v的意思是我们在传入一个数组
the v kind of just means that we're passing in an array
所以在这点上我们需要传入一个浮点数组
so we need to pass in a float array at this point
所以我们可以提供统一变量的位置，就像我们对其他SetUniform函数所做的那样
so we can provide the uniform location, as we do with all of our other SetUniform functions
我们在这里传入名字，计数是我们提供了多少矩阵
we're taking the name here, the count is how many matrices we're providing
我们只提供了一个矩阵来实现转置这个矩阵
we're providing just one matrix do we need to transpose the matrix
如果你们的矩阵是行主矩阵，这意味着它在内存中的排列方式
if your matrix was a row major matrix, which means that the way that it's laid out in memory
本质上是通过，仅仅通过行，而不是像glm那样通过列
is essentially to by, just by the rows, not by the columns like glm does
你们需要把它转置或者你们可以把它们从这里传过去
you need to transpose it either yourself or you can pass them through here
我们不需要转置它，因为我们用的是glm，它存储了它的矩阵
we don't need to transpose it, because we're using glm, which stores its matrix
比如主列中的元素，这是OpenGL所期望的
like elements in column-major, which is what OpenGL expects
所以我们可以在这里传入GL_FALSE
so we can pass in GL_FALSE over here
这个值本质上是一个指向浮点数组的指针
and the value is essentially a pointer to that float array
所以我们能做的就是传入矩阵的内存地址
so what we can do here is just pass in the memory address of matrix
然后这个基本上就是表示第0列和第0列中的元素
and then this basically just says column 0 and element 0 inside column 0
所以就那样，那就是glm存储数组的方式
so that's it, that's the way the glm stores it is as an array
但是我们实际可以用这些索引运算符来得到第一个元素的位置
but we can use these index operators to actually get the location of the first element
然后剩下的就会依次存储在内存中
and then the rest will be stored sequentially in memory
那么我们继续，调用GLCall，那就是我们需要做的全部
so there we go, let's around this with the GLCall, and that's really all we need to do
现在回到Application文件中
so now back in Application
我们像在这里一样设置统一变量，一次就好
we set the uniform as we do over here, just once is enough
我们可以每帧都设置它，就像我们对颜色做的那样
we can set it every frame, if we want to like we do with color
但既然它没有变化，我们就没必要这样做
but since it's not changing, there's no need for us to do that
如果我们按f5，现在希望它能运行
if we hit f5, now hopefully this will work
你们可以看到我们得到了一个小得多的东西
and you can see that we get something that's a lot smaller
但实际上它的纵横比是正确的，并且为了比较
but it is in fact the right aspect ratio, and for comparison
如果我们到这里，也许我们可以把源图形矩阵改成-4，4，-3，3
and if we go over here, maybe we change the source graphic matrix to be -4, 4 and -3, 3
我们仍然保持4:3的纵横比
we're still keeping that 4:3 aspect ratio
但我们实际上把它扩大了一倍，实际的几何形状应该小得多
but we've made it essentially twice as big, our actual geometry should be a lot smaller
你们可以看到我们创造了一个更小的ChernoLogo
and you can see we have created a smaller ChernoLogo
所以我可以回到另一个，因为它有点太小了
so I might revert back to the other one, because it's, this is a bit too small
但那本质上就是它的工作原理，通过指定这4个位置
but that's essentially how it works, by specifying these 4 positions
我们基本上定义了窗口的4种边界
we're basically specifying the 4 kind of boundaries of our window
那么左边是-2
so left is -2
如果我们试着在-2处画一个顶点位置，实际上我们只是为了好玩
if we try and draw a vertex position at -2, in fact let's just for fun
把这个变成-2，-2可能很难看到
move one this to -2, -2 might be hard to see
因为无论我们是在一种颜色的纹理上，而这个纹理挺合适的
because whether we're in a texture on a color, and the texture is our fit
但是如果我们把这个绘制成，如果我们把这个调成-2
but if we draw this to, if we were to change this to -2
它会在实际窗口的非常非常左的边缘
it would be at the very very left edge of our actual window
好了，但我会把它还原为0.5，这就是它的工作方式
okay, but I'll put it back to 0.5, and then that's the way this works
那么那是左边，那是右边，那是下边，那是上边
so that's the left edge, that's the right edge, that's the bottom edge, that's the top edge
然后这是近平面和远平面，这意味着如果我们尝试渲染一些东西
and then this is the near and far plane, which means if we try and render something
那是在外面，这个会变冷的
that's kind of outside, this it will get cold
不管怎么说，讲所有这些，我几乎快把自己搞糊涂了
anyway, I'm almost confusing myself, by talking about all of this
因为我们真的需要花20分钟在每个概念上
because we really need to spend like 20min on each of these concepts
在接下来的几期中我们会接触到的
which we will do in the following episodes
但我希望你们喜欢这种OpenGL数学入门
but I hope you guys enjoyed this kind of introduction to maths in OpenGL
就这个主题而言，我还能看到10到20集
I can just see like another 10 to 20 episodes just on this topic alone
让我知道什么是有意义的，什么是没有意义的
let me know what made sense, what didn't make sense
你们想看到更多的是什么东西
what you want to see more of
我可能会把一些演示放在一起，就像我在混合视频中做的那样
I'm gonna probably put together some presentations, like I did with the blending video
因为那真的能帮我解释这些东西
because that's really gonna help me explain this stuff
请在下面的评论中告诉我你们的想法
let me know what you thoughts are in the comments below
如果你们喜欢这个视频，就点击这个喜欢按钮
hit the like button, if you enjoyed this video
如果你们想支持本系列，请访问patreon.com/TheCherno
if you want to support this series, you can go to patreon.com/TheCherno
早点拿到这些视频，然后在一个私人的discord服务器上讨论这些事情
and get all these videos early, and get to talk about this stuff in a private kind of discord server
每个月都有机会在那里讨论这些系列的发展方向
and get access to a monthly hangout where we talk about the direction of these series
以及你们想要在生活中看到的一切，所有那些东西
and what you want to see in life, and all that stuff
真的有助于支持这个系列
and it really does help support this series
所以，和往常一样，非常感谢所有的支持者，是你们让这一切成为可能
so as always, huge thank you to all of my patreon supporters for making this possible
下次见，会有更多的数学知识哦，再见
I will see you guys next time, with a lot more maths, goodbye